<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A congratulatory Pindaric poem, for His Majesties safe deliverance from this hellish and true plot humbly dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lord Dunblaine, by C. P. ...</title>
            <author>C.P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1241</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13429246</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13429246</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99513</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56739)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99513)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 469:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A congratulatory Pindaric poem, for His Majesties safe deliverance from this hellish and true plot humbly dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lord Dunblaine, by C. P. ...</title>
                  <author>C.P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed to Walter Davis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:99513:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99513:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
            <head>A CONGRATULATORY Pindaric Poem, For His Majeſties Safe Deliverance from this Helliſh and True PLOT.</head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly Dedicated to the Right Honourable the Lord <hi>Dunblaine,</hi> by <hi>C. P.</hi> Gent.</head>
            <q>
               <l>Vicimus, ô magnis tandem exaudita piorum</l>
               <l>Voca Deis, nunc alma ſalus, nunc ſaecula curat</l>
               <l>Jupiter.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Barcl. Arg.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>TEll me, ye Great Divinities;</l>
               <l>Who dwell beyond the diſtant, and the arched Skies,</l>
               <l>Since you their Reign with Peace, and Love,</l>
               <l>Tell me why our Earthly <hi>Jove</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should ſo unhappy in his Subjects prove?</l>
               <l>Can it be a Puniſhment</l>
               <l>Which you from Heaven have ſent</l>
               <l>T'inflict on him that's Innocent?</l>
               <l>No, no, it cannot be</l>
               <l>It leſſens your Divinity,</l>
               <l>To ſend down Ills, upon the beſt of Men,</l>
               <l>And give the beſt of Princes ſo ſevere a Reign.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99513:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
            <lg n="2">
               <head>II.</head>
               <l>But hark! methinks I hear</l>
               <l>In th' ambent Air,</l>
               <l>A ſound, that grating ſtrikes my Liſtning ear,</l>
               <l>Which ſays the King muſt die,</l>
               <l>Nay inſtantly,</l>
               <l>Oh horrid and unheard of Blaſpemy!</l>
               <l>Look down, look down, thou mighty Thunderer,</l>
               <l>Who'ſt ſtill took care,</l>
               <l>To ſave, and to protect, thy great Ambaſſadour;</l>
               <l>See where he lyes</l>
               <l>Deſign'd the Peoples Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>Whoſe cruel minds ſo Diſobedient prove,</l>
               <l>The Government they all deteſt, as much as Treaſon love,</l>
               <l>And if they had the Power, the Rebels wou'd</l>
               <l>Once more imbrew their hands in their own Sovereigns Blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>III.</head>
               <l>Quit, quit, ye great Controulers of the Skies,</l>
               <l>Your happy Pallaces,</l>
               <l>And ſuddenly detect their damn'd Conſpiracies;</l>
               <l>Let not this Nation, which ye once thought dear,</l>
               <l>Neglected lye, but hear her prayer,</l>
               <l>And now once more deſcend, and pitty her,</l>
               <l>Unite her every part,</l>
               <l>And to that Union add a Loyal heart,</l>
               <l>That the great <hi>Maſs</hi> may joyntly move,</l>
               <l>Abroad commanding Fear, at Home creating Love.</l>
               <l>Then; then; we'll drain the Land from putrid Blood,</l>
               <l>And admit none, but what are Juſt and Good,</l>
               <l>Here Innocence alone ſhall Reign,</l>
               <l>And Loyalty and Peace admittance have again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <l>But now, and only now unhappy Iſle;</l>
               <l>On whom in former times the Gods would often Smile,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99513:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
               <l>And pour their Bleſſings down,</l>
               <l>Upon the obedient People, and the gentle Crown,</l>
               <l>Then; then; how Love and Peace,</l>
               <l>With Luxury and Eaſe</l>
               <l>Were joyn'd, as if they'd never part, or ever ceaſe,</l>
               <l>But now Sedition does o'reflow</l>
               <l>This once bleſt Land, though ſinking now,</l>
               <l>Sedition, with ſo black a dye,</l>
               <l>It aims at nothing leſs than Majeſty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>V.</head>
               <l>Thus the bold Sons of Earth</l>
               <l>Made their Attempts at Heaven, that gave 'em Birth.</l>
               <l>The Gods themſelves they did defie,</l>
               <l>Aſpiring to command even deſtiny.</l>
               <l>Mountains on Mountains ſtill were upward thrown,</l>
               <l>Whoſe towring height did almoſt reach the Sun.</l>
               <l>Thus did they think to ſhake <hi>Jove</hi>'s great and glorious Crown,</l>
               <l>Boldly they did their firſt Attempts perſue,</l>
               <l>For mounting, at the Gates of Heaven they flew,</l>
               <l>But to late found</l>
               <l>Their Bodies, with their Work, lade level with the Ground.</l>
               <l>This fate to the bold Rebels then was given,</l>
               <l>This Fate had Lucifer who fell from Heaven,</l>
               <l>Thus may all ſink from Earth to Hell,</l>
               <l>Like the damn'd falſe <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who dare againſt th' Almighty, or their Prince Rebel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <l>How often have the Fatal Siſters had</l>
               <l>Orders to cut the thread,</l>
               <l>On which did hang the Fate</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Charles</hi> the Juſt, the Good, the Great.</l>
               <l>How often in his Childhood did they run</l>
               <l>To force the high born Youth from's Throne;</l>
               <l>All this and more than this was done,</l>
               <l>For that great Crime of his, of being his Father's Son.</l>
               <l>Then Angels were from Heaven ſent,</l>
               <l>Who did thoſe threatning Ills prevent,</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:99513:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
               <l>Who ſtill maintain him in his Royal Seat,</l>
               <l>And guard his Perſon, and ſecure his State.</l>
               <l>Oh may theſe heavenly Guards for ever be</l>
               <l>Sufficient to protect him to Eternity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <l>But where's the <hi>Atlas</hi> of our ſinking State,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kelyn</hi> the Juſt, the Fortunate?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kelyn</hi> the Firſt, that ever cou'd</l>
               <l>Singly preſerve the Land from Blood,</l>
               <l>And at one time, ſerve Country, King, and God.</l>
               <l>What e're he did ſtill Conſcience was his Theam,</l>
               <l>All his Confeſſion ſtill from Conſcience came.</l>
               <l>Now, in the higheſt Sphere he ſure may move,</l>
               <l>Fam'd for Religion, Loyalty, and Love,</l>
               <l>Let him Juſt Heaven, for ſure from Heaven he came,</l>
               <l>In Life be Happy, and when Dead, in Fame,</l>
               <l>Let him, whilſt here below, from us receive</l>
               <l>All that a Land ſo much oblieg'd can give.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <l>Now; now; to Heaven let's offer up our Prayer,</l>
               <l>And thank th' Almighty, our Deliverer;</l>
               <l>Let's never ceaſe</l>
               <l>Our Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>'Till with our Incenſe we have fill'd the Skies;</l>
               <l>Through ev'ry Mouth let thanks be given,</l>
               <l>To that great Power above, that rules both Earth and Heaven;</l>
               <l>For by his Providence alone</l>
               <l>Cur King and Land's preſerv'd, and Crown:</l>
               <l>Oh! may Great <hi>Charles</hi> for ever be</l>
               <l>Secur'd againſt their Trechery!</l>
               <l>May he Live long, and happy Reign,</l>
               <l>And Peace be once brought back again.</l>
               <l>May Treaſon and the Traytor have an End,</l>
               <l>And t' Hell, as to their proper Center, tend.</l>
               <l>Thus may each Subject happy prove,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Charles</hi> be happy in each Subjects love.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>London, <hi>Printed for</hi> Walter Davis <hi>in</hi> Amen Corner. <hi>1683.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
